[Music]
this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se-radio.net
sc radio is brought to you by the ieee
computer society by ieee software
magazine
online at computer.org software
sc radio listeners we want to hear from
you please visit
se radio.net survey to share a little
information about your professional
interests and listening habits
it takes less than two minutes to help
us continue to make se radio even better
the responses to the survey are
completely confidential
that's s-e-radio.net survey
thanks for your support of the show we
look forward to hearing from you soon
i'm adam conrad and this is software
engineering radio today we're talking
with jason meller
jason is the ceo and founder of collide
jason has dedicated his career to
building products and tools that enable
security experts to successfully defend
western interests from sophisticated and
organized global cyber threats
jason thank you for coming on software
engineering radio today
oh thanks for having me i'm really
excited to talk about this today because
there are so many tech stacks out there
for people to build their applications
with
i only have experience in some of them
but i'm really excited to see how one
thinks about
building a tech stack for a new
greenfield project so to start at a very
high level
what is a tech stack specifically the
stack part
yeah so the way that i think about it is
i think a tech sac is really
a series of foundational technologies so
you're talking about frameworks
languages
services and together they should be
best suited towards achieving a
specific software engineering goal you
know obviously
business goals are important there but
it's really about specific software
engineering goals and requirements
and those are the components that really
make the decision tree for
choosing a check stack our tech stack
really important and why don't the
business goals play into that that's
actually interesting i've never heard
that
particular line of reasoning before
because business goals should really be
divorced
from specific technology choices and i
have to deal with this all the time
because i'm sort of dual hatting in my
startup
as the ceo and cto so it's really
important that i don't conflate
a business goal which is you know i want
to build a specific type of product that
has these specific features that meets
these
specific use cases and then try to use
that
foundational set of requirements to then
move forward
towards directly to technologies we want
to really take that and take a
separate step and actually define
specific software engineering
architecture and requirements that
should inform the tech stack decision
making
so you don't want to just jump from one
thing to another if you're really
experienced and you have a very small
team
that's often what happens and that's
fine if you're making really good
decisions
but often if you skip that step you're
actually losing some fidelity in what
you're actually trying to accomplish
and you really should start thinking
about software engineering goals
specifically as they relate to
technologies
you know software is a means to an end
and at the end of the day software may
not even necessarily be
the solution to a specific business goal
and so
you have to kind of just take that extra
step and really understand is software
engineering even required for this
business goal
and if it is that's when you want to
start thinking about a technology stack
that's complementary
that's really interesting so you're
still saying that it informs the
decision right so for example if the ceo
at the company says well i want
a recommendation engine or i want
recommendations for the customer that's
it's like implicitly saying oh you might
want to think about python because
recommendation implies artificial
intelligence
and right you know python's a really
good tech stack or language for
for ai development i think that's a
really great example though because
the way that i think about that as a ceo
is you stated it perfectly
you know we want to provide
recommendations for our customers for x
y and z
well depending on the scale and how many
customers you have
you may not need any software
engineering for that you may just need
some people
to actually go and manually curate those
recommendations and then email them
to prospective clients and existing
customers so really when
we have the software engineering goal
would be there okay we need to achieve
that goal
that business requirement for this scale
and these other
additional more technological
requirements that are sort of embedded
in that
so i think it's really important that
you tease that out because oftentimes a
lot of the high level goals that you
have at very early stages in your
organization
don't necessarily require software
engineers to actually go in
start typing code into a code editor you
can actually solve them and actually
test the merit of the business idea
before you've invested a lot of time and
money
into actually writing software against
it which is the most expensive part of
the process
yeah i'm thinking back to what if the
startups
i used to work at many years ago the way
they started
their application was a wordpress site
so because i was going to say was
technology right now is sort of embedded
into every company so i think it's
probably i don't think you're saying
that you don't use technology at all
it's just that
what facets of your business are
actually using technology i think is
kind of the
right thing you're sort of striving
towards here and i think back to like i
said i was at a startup
where their very first iteration of
their business was a wordpress site
in a series of craigslist ads so they
were leveraging technology but they
didn't use the software engineering
piece of that
for businesses that you're talking with
or or your friends that are starting
companies
what areas do you think require software
engineering from day one and what areas
do you think you can leverage existing
software solutions
yeah so i would encourage founders that
are out there that
really want to test the validity of an
idea right because that's how most
startups start you you have an idea
and you really want to test the validity
of that idea in a market
you want to test whether or not people
are willing to pay for that now
a poor way of doing that is to just ask
people and what you'll find when you do
that
is people aren't necessarily honest you
know they don't want to insult you
and they'll sort of say at a high level
yeah maybe i would use that but when it
really comes down to it would they
actually open up their wallet and pay
the money
that's a completely different level of
feedback so you want to get that level
of feedback
so the first thing that you really need
to think about is how can i test
the theory actually get people to pay
money to me
for providing a service or some kind of
benefit
and how can i do that in a way that
requires the least amount of software
engineering
and the reason why you want the least
amount of software engineering is can
you test the validity of the idea before
you need to raise capital
or you need to invest your own time and
your own capital into actually writing
code
which once you've written code now you
have technology debt you have bugs
you have infrastructure you have a lot
of decisions that we're going to be
talking about in this podcast
but if you can avoid the majority of
that and still test your idea
then once that idea is vetted you're
going to know a lot more about it and
you're going to actually be able to pick
a better tech stack when it is time to
automate that business opportunity
okay so let's assume that we know
there's going to be at least
one developer maybe it's yourself who
has to make that investment
and what comes with that investment
right out the gate is i have to store
this data somewhere so i'm probably
paying for a database server
and the application itself needs to be
stored somewhere maybe it's a
downloadable application or it's a web
application so we at least know
one person and one tech stack is
required to accomplish our mission
first question i have for you is how do
you know
whether to build it yourself or buy it
so a common example of this
is devops infrastructure it's very easy
to spin something up now in aws with
bean stock elastic bean stock
or you could actually just buy the whole
system with heroku
or some service like that so for the
very beginning you know you have one
stack
how would you go about making that
decision on build versus buy
so let's uh review the the scenario that
you just gave me
i think that when you are if you are a
person you know it's just you
you have your idea and you have enough
software engineering knowledge that
doesn't necessarily mean
you know definitively that you can build
the whole thing but you're willing to
bet on yourself to actually build it out
then the thing that you want to do is
you want to optimize
where you're actually you know filling
your own knowledge gaps
with services that are already
structured so so for me personally
i'm a ruby on rails engineer i know how
to build web apps
like you know like the back of my hand
but the part where i always struggle
with is really getting into the weeds in
terms of
the persistence layer like how am i
going to make sure that i'm running
postgres with the uh you know the right
modifications how am i gonna backup
postgres i'm gonna make sure that it's
you know has high availability how am i
gonna do all these things
and that's a series of knowledge and
capability that i don't necessarily want
to
slow down and have to learn in order to
get my idea out there well that's a
perfect example where you might want to
you know reach for a managed service
like heroku has
managed uh postgres and it's a great
option for folks who really just
want that problem solved for them so
they can focus on the business logic of
their actual application
now if you are someone who actually has
the opposite scenario where
you are really passionate about you know
you're an sre you're really passionate
about operations
but you don't know much about building
web apps that's when you might want to
reach for a consultancy
and then have them really kind of help
you choose
the right foundational technologies to
base that on but when you're at this
early stage and you really
have meager resources to work with the
actual technology choices that you make
today
are really going to be ones that should
be optimized for how much can you
participate in the process directly
and if you can't participate in the
process directly who are the folks
that you can get access to and what does
their skills and expertise actually look
like and then you should really
you know optimize the tech stack to
their experience because that's going to
maximize their chances of helping you
and i think a lot of engineers and a lot
of founders fret a lot
over the tech stack there's a lot of
anxiety when choosing tech stacks
because
that's really going to determine the
quality of life or the day-to-day for
that engineer
you know whatever language is being
chosen the framework and the maturity of
the framework
the maturity of those apis how good is
the documentation
but at the end of the day if we're
talking about really small teams and
shoestring budgets
we really want to optimize for how much
of this work can you actually
do yourself and invest your own time
versus having to raise capital
and pay a lot of money so that you can
support technologies that you don't
necessarily understand
right so first do complementary skill
sets so if you're not a devops person
let heroku handle the dev ops for you so
you can focus on the application layer
which brings me to my next point you're
talking about layers here the
persistence layer the application layer
or even you know other layers like the
mobile layer
so what are the common layers of a tech
stack that you consider when you're
thinking about technologies
yeah so data persistence is a huge one
and i think that's where you can get a
mixture of technologies
obviously lately postgres has just been
killing it in terms of actual
relational database and they're really
good at now document database storage
so that's a fine choice for i think a
lot of early stage projects
where there's a lot of potential
consternation around okay you know we
might have a lot of events and we have a
lot of things going in
are we going to need something like
elastic are we going to need other
document storage mechanisms
i think postgres has you know proven
that you can actually be
multifaceted technology and actually do
each one of those components relatively
well so i think that's a great choice
and then redis is another obvious choice
for people who just want really fast
reads rights and
you know hot storage for either event
queuing and things like that i think
redis is a fine choice for both of those
things so
the majority of projects that i'm
working on those are usually the two
foundational technologies that i'm
choosing for data persistence
but there's data processing there's api
slash business logic
there's the user interface and if we're
talking about a web application that
might also
you know have native apps as well you
know that can live in multiple areas
then you have infrastructure which can
be considered hosting or operations
devops and then finally you have just
the generic structure
of how the stack works you know isaiah
are we looking at microservices are we
going to need to be able to bring in
some sort of containerization or
kubernetes or can we go with a more
majestic monolith approach
where pretty much everything is in the
same exact code base we don't really
have to worry about
how these things how these different
components communicate with each other
because we're just using one language
and everything's sort of globally
available to us
and so those are all components i think
that make up a tech stack
a common tech stack at least and you're
hinting at this that there's like a
decision tree that you use to evaluate
oh if
thinking about web choose possibly a
monolith you're thinking about
some sort of view layer that might be on
mobile as well too consider
native mobile applications at a very
high level what kind of decisions are
you making for approaching technologies
yeah so i think you have to think about
the customer experience that you are
really going for and work backwards
like for instance at collide we knew
that we were going to have a major
slack app component to what we were
building
and so it was really important to us
that whatever technologies we chose of
the hood they had
a lot of maturity in interacting with
the slack sdk
we don't have any requirements for
building a native app
on either mac os or things like that or
on ios or android so
it wasn't really important for us to you
know either garner a lot of experience
in
you know java or objective c or swift
um and if we needed to go that route you
know we had you know some javascript
experience so that we can
you know leverage react data for the
ionic framework instead
in terms of the web application we
wanted to really think through
all right how can we enable
our engineers to build features
all the way from back end to front end
with relatively little front end
experience because we didn't want to
necessarily shell out for
a large army or front end engineers that
were really going to wait for
you know these bespoke apis to be built
so we really uh
focused on server-side template
rendering which is a different choice
that i think a lot of folks are making
lately when they're really thinking
about building you know these
cordoned off apis and then sending all
that stuff to something like react
we chose a completely different route
because it was really important for us
to allow our three or four engineers
that were working on the product
to feel unable to actually build a
feature from all the way from conception
to the front end and actually get it out
the door without having to pull in three
or four
different people that had a
specialization in a particular area
so those are all things that are really
uh tied into the tech
stack decisions that we made at collide
which are really optimized towards
small teams empowering our engineers to
be as full stack as they possibly could
and if there are large gaps in our
knowledge we actually are using heroku
so that we don't have to spend a lot of
our time discussing you know operations
in general you know we're just trusting
that heroku is doing the right thing for
us and in general they are
now one thing that i think a lot of
engineers fret about and ctos as well
is what is the customer impact going to
be about these decisions how much do
customers really care about back end
architecture and
tech stacks and this came up a lot when
we were discussing
what frameworks and choices that we
wanted to make especially on the
operations side
really worried that oh if we couldn't
get this the level of customer data
segregation that we wanted
you know people were going to really
kind of you know be upset by that that
could
impact sales and the reality is that
even for our security startup where i
think we have the most scrutiny out of
the majority of sas companies that are
out there there's not a lot of scrutiny
into
a lot of those in the weeds decisions
around data tenancy
and how much of the operations are we
actually handling in fact i think a lot
of our customers felt
at ease with the fact that we had
offloaded that tool existing
organizations that have already passed
their sock to they've already passed a
variety of different
compliance you know achievements and i
think that at the end of the day
that's actually what puts them at ease
that there's a lot that's
easy to predict about our stack and they
don't have to feel like they have to
evaluate
a lot of custom engineering a lot of
custom components that
you might feel compelled to build that's
probably the same decision that ceos
make too right so it's like
the ceo cares about the recommendation
engine they don't care about python
similarly the customer cares about
does this app work is it fast and is it
secure
and so then the text decision very much
based on
the solution you choose that enables
high performance or high availability or
high
you know security there are security
plugins that are baked in
to the application stack so for example
you might want to choose rails because
there are plenty of plugins out there
that handle auth for you so you don't
have to build it yourself which is a
pretty common tenant for security is you
know don't roll your own off
i actually want to touch more on the
team piece i noticed that when you were
talking about choosing technologies
a lot of it was focused around for you
enabling small teams to work in the full
stack experience but how much
do you also weigh into the tech stack in
terms of right tool for the right job so
for example
it's really easy to choose javascript
because it's sort of like a one-trick
pony for a lot of things however
there are some good reasons to use
javascript on the back end for your
particular use case like
the slack example i would think that a
working with the slack api would involve
a lot of events so event based
programming is probably a good tech
stack for that so regardless of your
team makeup
choosing something like node which is
very much event based would be good also
erlang or elixir
are very much event based so how do you
weigh in right tool for the right job
while also weighing in the sort of team
layout of
how your team's going to be set up so i
think in terms of prioritizing those
you want to optimize over team
productivity
and empowerment over anything else
because i think
a lot of engineers and ctos they sit
down and they try to dispassionately
you know make these choices like it's a
scientific exercise
where you know they're not bringing in
their own personal biases and we're
looking at the software engineering
requirements
and we're going to make a very rational
decision
based objectively on these requirements
but in practice
that never happens there's so much bias
from either previous experience with
these technologies
or actual desires that you end up making
these
arguments that are really if you distill
them down almost psychologically
they're really you just advocating for
the thing that you feel the most
comfortable with
and so collide we try to shortcut a lot
of that and you know there's engineers
that you know are going to be the
powerhouses in your organization they're
going to be the ones that
in essence are building the majority of
the application and what you don't want
to do and then there's types of
engineers that
are really good at recognizing when
those engineers are
you know going off the rails maybe
they're doing something that's not going
to scale or they need to
you know inject some computer science
knowledge into the situation so that you
know you're building something with an
efficient algorithm
there's those types of engineers as well
but i've always found
that the powerhouse engineers you're
going to enable them to be so much more
productive
if you just choose the technologies that
they're most familiar with before you
even get
into i think a lot of the software
engineering goals when you have that
latitude that's an important caveat
a good example of this when you don't
have that latitude is when you're
looking at
building software for platforms that
just have a lingua franca like
i think a good example this is ios
sure there's ionic you know there's you
know react native there's a bunch of
ways that you can leverage
existing javascript skill sets to build
a pretty good
ios application but if your main goal
and what is special about your
organization requires the best possible
ios app out there you need to build it
in objective c
or swift or swift ui like that's just
that's just how the platform is designed
like you're going to get the best
performance you're going to have access
to the most native apis
like you just need to choose those
technologies and you don't have that
level of latitude there
if that's what the core of your business
is which is an ios
application if that's what your decision
is but if that isn't the core of your
business and you just need like a reader
app
that's when you can really start
optimizing for the experience of the
team and then start choosing some of
those javascript
frameworks and technologies that allow
you to arrive at a pretty good
application
and then over time what's nice about
some of these decisions
is that when those things become more
important you can start
looking to hire an ios engineer who can
then start transforming some of these
web view based
screens and actually upgrading them into
full native experiences and you can do
that piecemeal
when it's appropriate for your business
but i think a lot of engineers
don't take into their own their own
skill set a new account because they
want to choose the best technologies
for the best outcome but the best
outcome is the software actually gets
written in a timely manner
you know under or at budget you know and
it's something that actually ends up
working
and so if you choose the right
technologies to produce the best outcome
in theory but in practice it doesn't get
done on time or there's a lot of bugs
because you're inexperienced with that
technology
then you haven't chosen the best option
so my advice to everybody out there is
try to figure out okay we know at a high
level it's a team that you've worked
with before
it's going to be this selection of
people that are going to be the most
productive
and let's optimize for them to just get
the code out the door
using the things that they're most
comfortable with and then if you're the
type of person that can
augment them it's likely that you're
going to be able to learn
whatever you know language primitives
are necessary for you to be able to
apply your computer science knowledge to
make sure their code is going to work at
scale i think that makes sense for the
no brainer tech stacks like you
mentioned with ios
there's sort of two follow-up questions
that i'm very curious about and we can
tackle them one at a time but it's a
high level
one is what if you're a web developer
and it's you and your friend or
co-founders
and you realize that the solution is an
ios app and neither of you have ios
experience
to your earlier point you would probably
hire a consulting firm but you're also
both developers so do you just kind of
suck it up
and try ios or do you go well we know
javascript so we're going to try
reactive until we're out of our league
how do you kind of approach that one
when there's sort of a tech mismatch but
you both fundamentally believe in the
product
i think at that stage when you're it's
more of a proving ground i think that
it's okay for you to have a sub-optimal
decision i think if you're two
co-founders and you know how to code
both of you it would be i think foolish
for you to choose a technology stack
that you're gonna have to learn on the
fly while you're trying to test your
idea
even if that technology stack is the
most optimal for building
on that platform and i think ios i
mentioned you may not have that latitude
there
but the reality is is that you may not
have the latitude
of time to actually learn the the
technology stack on the fly like that
now a lot of these languages and
frameworks like swift is great like
if you already can code in javascript
it's likely you can pick up swift
relatively well
and fast but the problem is is that you
don't really have time
like there's different levels of
competency when you're coding and you
need to be able to get in the flow
really fast when you're building an
entirely new idea
you need to be able to just get out of
the mindset of every time that you need
to do something
you're trying to translate your old
javascript knowledge into
what is the language equivalent of this
and swift what is the best practice of
this in swift
it ends up disrupting that flow and if
you can get flow a lot faster
and it's just the two of you and you
need to prove out an idea having like
30 or 40 milliseconds extra of latency
on interactions
isn't going to make or break you know
your ideas success
you are going to create tech debt down
the road but that's okay you were going
to create it anyway even if you knew
swift
like you just you don't know what lies
ahead of you in terms of how the product
is going to change based on the initial
feedback
what scalability you need to change and
so it's really important that you get
your idea out there
and not worry about i think a lot of
micro optimizations that are going to be
necessary
way later in the business after the
product is already somewhat successful
yeah and if it's you and a co-founder
friend and it's a side project and
you're
excited about learning swift and you
already have some javascript experience
i think yeah it totally makes sense to
go okay
we're willing to take this leap of faith
it's probably the right move anyway
and it's not as high of a barrier of
entry as probably objective c and
we're willing to invest in that but like
you said if it's a critical business
where you've just
both quit your jobs and you really want
to get this out the door yeah maybe it's
okay to make a sub-optimal decision
because
pre-optimization as they say is the root
of all evil so it's not
it's no good to pre-optimize if your
business is going to fall flat
now the other question i had was sort of
more about a more established team
and this is i've seen this happen a
couple of times before is i
like your reasoning behind choosing to
optimize around team productivity
though it might seem a little
short-sighted because you have to hire
folks and if you hire folks
you have to look at a much longer term
hiring path so i think that also makes a
decision there too because
what i've seen this happens a couple
times is you've got a team
who's all knowing gender really well and
they optimize around a technology that
works but it's probably not like you
said the lingua franca the example of
this would be
using closure for the web or haskell
like haskell has the assad
closure has luminous for web frameworks
you
probably use functional programming
languages specifically haskell probably
more in the pure math
r d world but you've got a bunch of
folks who just know haskell really well
but then you have to hire folks to teach
them haskell and you probably could have
a hyper
performing team that writes the least
amount of code because that's kind of
how these functional languages work
but then your challenge is well we all
know this so of course we're going to
choose haskell but
what if you have to hire 10 more people
in the next year so how does that factor
into evolving that team beyond what you
have right now today
yeah i think there's a lot of anxiety
about this when picking tech stacks
because i i do think people
try to choose check tech stacks that are
really going to
allow them a large selection of
individuals juniors
seniors and you know staff engineers
that you know of all different types of
experiences but i i think that the fears
around that are a little bit overblown
and what you find is that even if you
pick a more
obscure programming language you don't
need
thousands of people coming into your
organization within a year like that's
pretty rare like shopify is a good
example of
you know we need to do that because
we're growing at a huge pace and we need
to get a lot of ruby engineers and there
just
aren't enough out there but that's a
pretty it's a high-class problem to have
if you look at some of the more obscure
organizations that started off with like
i think a weird programming language
i think reddit used lisp as a good
example of this early on in their y
combinator days
and they originally
were able to find a sufficient amount of
engineers even in something i think
obscures lisp for
or back in web engineering in order to
meet that requirement
so i think that it's going to change the
pool of people that you have available
to you
but oftentimes a lot of these popular
languages and frameworks
you're also competing against some of
the
largest most well-funded organizations
that are out there
you know the fangs of the world that are
looking for those same people and
they're willing to pay them
50 more in salary and benefits than
you're going to be able to afford
and so if you go to with a more obscure
language that maybe isn't in high demand
you might find some really passionate
people
that really love that language that are
going to be very turnkey
into your organization and all the
different ways that you code today
because they have the same stylistic
preferences
and they're not their salary isn't
obscene because
you know the facebooks or the googles of
the world aren't vying for those
particular skill sets
right so even though there's probably
more security tools around php
and laravel if you chose something like
clojurescript
in the closure stack you just might
people who see
the job description for closure and go
oh wow
i can actually get the work enclosure
full time i would be willing to
take a salary cut if it meant that i got
to develop in the tool set that i really
like
so that's an interesting tradeoff would
you trade a more robust
you know say security framework or not
having to roll your own off versus
a stack where you know you can hire
folks yes absolutely i think
well i i think that the i think it would
be challenging to pick a stack today
where you had no ability to hire anyone
like i think that there's enough
diversity out there and this is
something that i think people are trying
to change about the web which
i'm not a big fan of like i think one of
the best parts about the web
is that we can choose whatever language
we want to build the back end and the
you know the end users really have no
idea as long as the html is served
served in an efficient manner and my
browser can render it of course
javascript has to be used on the front
end
but i reject the notion that we want
this monolithic language
just like we have with ios with swift
and objective-c
on the web like that to me i think is
reducing
the diversity of choice that's out there
and i think that
you're going to see a lot of people who
are really passionate about the
languages they use just
exit the job market because they don't
necessarily want to
code in javascript all day i certainly
am not a giant fan of javascript but
it's something that
i felt i had to learn in order to uh you
know build at least a competent front
end for a web application
but if i'm going to choose a back end i
want to choose something that i'm going
to get some level of enjoyment out
every day and i can find others around
me that that feel the same way
so i wouldn't necessarily say that there
are choices out there
i mean i'm sure there are like no one's
going to code their
like you're not going to get a lot of
cobol developers that are great at web
development like that's just not going
to happen
but the reality is is i think for the
majority of choices out there
if you in the past have been able to
write a web app for you know that
particular language
using that particular language then i
think that you'll be in a position where
you're gonna be able to hire
people and there might be different
types of people they might come from
different geographic locations they
might look different than you
but they're gonna be people nevertheless
that are willing to roll up their
sleeves and help you
so i think you can optimize for both i
think you can optimize for a language
that you're comfortable with
that has a degree of maturity around it
and it's going to be suited towards the
skill set of the current engineers
you will have a hiring pool guaranteed
it may take you a little bit longer
you might have to reach a little bit
farther but they're out there especially
if you're willing to embrace remote work
yeah and honestly you could probably get
away with not writing javascript at all
because a lot of these languages have
compiled to javascript so you can still
fundamentally write in that language
without actually ever having to touch
raw javascript yourself so
there's still that benefit there too
what other sort of before we move on to
sort of the common tech stacks
what other heuristics do you look for
that maybe we haven't talked about so
far in terms of evaluating criteria for
choosing the right tech stack
yeah i think one thing that is okay to
do i mean this is a
correlation not necessarily causal but
you should look at you know
the top companies that are out there
that you admire that are in your field
and look at the tech stacks that they've
been successful with i think for a
variety of reasons one is they've proven
that they can reach this incredible
level of success
with the tech stack and that has proven
that there isn't just this
giant limiter upstream that's going to
prevent you from
reaching this incredible goal that you
have in mind so i think that's important
and number two is they've probably
invented a lot of libraries and
frameworks that are going to be
important for you as you build out
either a competing solution or a
complimentary solution
in that field so i would definitely take
a look at that i mean a good example of
this was
i read an article by someone who follows
the y combinator companies i think they
wrote it in like
2019 or maybe early 2020 and of the top
50 y commenter
if you add up their valuations in 2019 i
think it was something like
175 or 176 billion dollars
in total valuation and if you look at
that over
half 92 billion of it is from companies
that said
that they have one primary back-end
language and that
language was ruby and i think that if
you look at those
startups and you look at coinbase and
you look at stripe and you look at
airbnb
and you see a lot of complementary goals
that you have like maybe you want to
build a killer api for
you know helping ship products like you
want to build the stripe for ups and
fedex and dhl
like you have the ability maybe ruby
would be a great programming languages
there because stripe has
built such a great foundational set of
libraries for building
incredible apis or maybe if you're doing
something in crypto or
you know blockchain coinbase has proven
out that you can build a significant
portion of that in ruby
obviously they're using c plus as well
and a number of other technologies
but in terms of the user experience and
the majority of the application that
customers actually see
a lot of that is in ruby and it's
scaling and i think since this article
was written like the valuations of the
companies that i just mentioned has
probably
tripled and so it's a good example of
it's okay to look at who's being
successful when
i think the counter argument to that is
all right is that really a function of
their success or is that really a
function of when they were founded
because
strike was i think found in like 2010
that was when rails was really
at its apex in terms of popularity but i
think coinbase
base is a good counter example of that
you know they were founded much earlier
they still chose i think a technology
back then that a lot of people would
have dismissed as
you know um in their fall or winter in
terms of the maturity level
and they're going to be fading out soon
and they've been able to revitalize it
so
i think you can impact your own reality
especially if you end up being a
really successful hyper growth
organization
today's sponsor is spot by netapp the
cloud automation platform that makes it
easy to deliver continuously optimized
infrastructure at the lowest possible
cost
get the most out of your cloud
investments by automating cloud
infrastructure to ensure performance
reduce complexity and optimize costs
their machine learning and automation
scale to exactly meet application needs
using the most efficient mix of
instances and pricing models
eliminating the risks of
over-provisioning and cloud waste
leverage spot with all leading cloud
platforms services and tools
check them out at spot.io se radio where
you can find more information
request a demo or even start a free
trial
so i'm looking at toby which is the
software quality company they release
every year the
top programming languages for each year
so what i want to do is actually want to
look through
from the highest to lowest again i just
basis solely on the tob rankings which
is a lot a lot of people use i think
stack overflow uses the same rankings
roughly when they do their developer
survey every year
they just look at what are the most in
demand languages for software developers
so i kind of want to just go through the
most popular
ones and look at the tech stacks for
those languages and just kind of get
your opinion based on the heuristics
you've talked about
how you would think about using these
languages when building these
software greenfield projects so you know
from the very beginning we're looking at
javascript
java and python so starting with
javascript what are you looking at there
in terms of text stack yeah obviously
javascript is well suited towards the
web i mean it was a foundational web
technology ecmascript
and i think that you're going to want to
choose javascript
if you're building i think a rich
client-side
application and when i think about rich
client-side applications i don't mean
the settings page of a sas right like
that's not something that really
requires this
level of reactivity where you need to
pull in you know something like
components and the react framework in
general like i think of
companies like medium where they spent
like the core of their business
is a wysiwyg editor and it has to be
perfect it has to
not have a single issue it has if you
type a character
and there's even a little bit of latency
the user experience is
broken it's dead and i think that when
the stakes are that high
that's when you want to reach for some
of these incredibly performant
you know front-end frameworks like react
now when it comes to typescript
i think the really interesting thing
about typescript and the web in general
is that
everything over http is like it's all
strings and then you do a lot of
conversion of data into types
and i've always felt like at least
personally for me when i'm using
technologies like typescript i feel like
i'm constantly fighting
these implicit conversions because
everything i'm getting over is
essentially text like over the wire
and so i have a lot of work where i'm
doing a lot of conversion there and then
i don't necessarily care about the type
of this particular thing in the side of
this json object
it's like i find myself when i'm writing
typescript like i'm really
glad that i have all these great ide
recommendations that i maybe i'm writing
the wrong thing or i'm assuming a nil
when i or no when i
think i should have something there but
ultimately i feel like i'm constantly
fighting
the lack of standardization of the data
that i'm getting over the wire when it
comes to typescript versus when i really
need typing
like if i'm using something like go or
i'm writing in swift
like that's when types feel really
helpful and useful when i'm really
plugging into operating system apis that
have strong types already associated
with them
because that's how they were built you
know you bring up an interesting point
about the
application types you know the one i was
thinking of that i thought you were
going to go
with was like dashboards so companies
like salesforce
log rocket keep you know the sort of
like
logging and analytics tools where you
actually see dashboards in real time
with you know graphics or d3 for
something like that that's where i would
figure
something like javascript is super
useful because these languages
and these frameworks like react or
angular or view they're all very
front-end
focused and client-side focused like you
said but they also have extensions for
things like d3
so you can get rich visualizations in
real time
with that sort of client feature-rich
updates that
make it very compelling to focus on the
front end i actually didn't consider the
medium example i think that's a really
good example
of something that i would have never
conventionally thought is very front and
focus but like you said
you should be able to click into the
letter j and it instantly shows up in
your editor
without any sort of issues and if you're
doing type you know
i was about to say type checking but
spell checking in the editor you want to
be able to see that it actually
finds the spelling error immediately
right like you said the ui should be
extremely responsive
down to the millisecond so that's a good
use case for that that totally makes
sense now what
another use case that i'll bring up just
to close this out a little bit
is network latency because i think a lot
of people discount this
when you are trying to ship products
that aren't necessarily
where your customer base isn't going to
be necessarily in the continental us
latency becomes a real issue you know
people are farther away than cdns than
you might assume
and then the ability for you to really
do that server round trip when they
click
you know the options drop down in the
settings menu if it's going to take now
500 milliseconds or a
full second to do that that is not going
to be acceptable probably and then you
might want to reach
for more of a client-side you know
javascript approach because you can
offload a lot of that work in developing
countries where
just the network connectivity isn't
going to be where it's at but what's so
funny is
the opposite is true is once you start
getting in over to android
you really need to think about building
android apps more natively
you know using java and the reason why
is
android's javascript engine isn't as
good as ios so once you start loading
everything
in javascript in you know chrome's you
know web browser on android or whatever
web browser you choose
you're just going to have a really
sub-par experience because
v8 is great on the desktop but it's not
so great compared to
what apple is doing with their built-in
you know silicon
like they just have a much better
performance story there and it may not
be the right
technology to choose if you are really
want to build a web app that's going to
primarily used on android devices you
might want to go native
so are you then anti-node if you wanted
to go javascript the whole way through
it sounds like
well i think we talked about this
earlier event based programming is
probably a good use case for node but it
sounds like to you
if it's very client heavy stick with the
front-end technologies for javascript
but are you
saying don't go javascript full bar down
to the node layer
yeah i think if you have unless you have
teams that are super experienced in node
i would avoid it i think there's a lot
better modern choices for event-based
programming today
you know we were making fun of it
earlier around slack and like we
actually built all of our venting in
rails and ruby uh for all of our slack
events and we just have asynchronous
processing and we have
it's incredibly uh against like i think
the norms of the language like there's
event machine in ruby that allows you
some degree of eventing but like
ruby doesn't really have really good
parallel processing and things like that
it's just missing these core features in
the language that make it possible
it has a concept of threads but they're
green threads and they you know you have
the
global interpreter locked and all these
other things that really just prevent
you from
really getting that multi-core
performance maybe that you want to do
but
in some ways when you have uh i think a
lot of people abuse those features like
you know and go it's really easy to
start reaching for threads and i think a
lot of parallelization of tasks
and then you end up with i think a lot
of timing issues and then something that
maybe
didn't really need that level of
optimization now has a lot of bugs in it
that are really hard to tease out and
when it comes to something as simple as
you know we need to receive some events
like
when someone changes their like a web
hook from stripe or in essence that's
what we're getting from slack
it's pretty easy to process and we can
do process-based parallelization
on the ruby side and i don't even have
to think about it and i don't have to
think about
multi-threading and like all these weird
you know side effects from setting
instance variables like i just don't
have to think about it like
compute is really cheap like just if you
can get away with
parallelizing things which is pure
compute and spinning up 80 ruby
processes
it's not going to be that expensive
compared to
the actual true costs which are going to
be really related to the people that are
building it at least at first
and i think shopify is a really great
example of you know
if they switch to a different technology
stack would they be saving a lot of
money on the
compute side and i i think that they did
the exercise and the answer was maybe a
little bit but it would be such a huge
the swishing costs would be so massive
for them that it would be nowhere near
worth it
so i think you've pretty much sold
people on ruby because you said you guys
use it yourselves that collide and then
obviously what was it 92 percent
of the value that was extracted from the
y combinator company's valuations was
around ruby on rails is that right
something like that it was 92 billion
out of 176 billion so i think uh
52 percent or so yeah we know ruby
and rails rails is pretty much the big
one for web there's also sinatra which i
think is kind of more of the lightweight
version of that i think the the analogy
for python is
django is to real as sinatra is the
flask just
briefly do you have any rubrics you use
for
deciding whether you should do something
in sinatra versus rails on ruby
yeah i actually have a very strong
opinion about this because
i see engineers all the time saying you
know what
we don't really need all the bells and
whistles of rails
or django or whatever the framework is
and we can go with like the the light
like we just need to be able to open up
some routes and you know like express
let's you do and just define some
functions that are going to return some
html like that's what we need
and we don't need like this heaviness
that comes with the framework
and i don't understand where that
mentality really comes from because
yes there is a degree of heaviness in
terms of how much memory you're using as
these processes run
but in general you're free to not call
apis that you don't need and i think a
lot of these frameworks are very modular
and they allow you to extract out
or import only the things that you
really need from them and oftentimes
what starts off as like a sinatra app or
an express app
sometimes needs to graduate to something
way more powerful than that
and now you're looking at a total
rewrite and i think that if you're
already working with a team that's
familiar with the i think the beefier
framework
go with that because i think the
performance characteristics between
these frameworks for the same language
end up being pretty close and it's not
like you have this order of magnitude
performance increase with going with the
lighter weight framework
usually it just means you have to learn
a completely different api for doing the
same things
and i think a lot of the performance
gains that you think are there are
actually not there
in real world use cases so i would put
those
to the side unless you truly know and
you see all the way out
five years from now that you're not
going to need 99 of the features of
like a django or rails then maybe it
makes sense
for you to write something in sinatra
but i just don't see that use case
actually happening
in reality often enough and i try to
shut down those conversations because
if we can fit in the monolith in our end
we're gonna do that because it just
gives us so many
synergistic advantages in terms of
productivity of putting everything in a
majestic model of today versus having
like as soon as we create a separate
micro services thing like that opens up
this whole can of worms of
all right now we need to think about the
communication infrastructure
how are we going to now containerize
this stuff how are we going to
orchestrate
all these containers to deploy at the
same time how we're going to release as
soon as you add one micro service
all those questions become relevant and
then they start taking away from the
things that
you know might be more important at the
time which is validating your product
one thing i might add to your heuristics
which i think i guess we just didn't
cover which you sort of brought up in
this example is
developer community i think also adds to
the decision tree here because
i think in the ruby community rails is
pretty much the standard
but i found actually that in python more
teams tend to lean towards flask instead
of django for some reason so
even though flask is probably a closer
analogy to sinatra
i found that more teams seem to pivot
towards flask in the python community
whereas in the ruby community they're
very much still focused on rails so
do you think that plays a part into it
as well too because i think probably if
you talk to python folks they'd probably
choose flask over django
in 2021. yeah i would agree with that
that's generally true and i think that
when you do choose a specific
language you want to look toward the
companies that
you admire and you know you want to
emulate and go on the well-trodden path
because there's just so many advantages
of being the little minnow that gets to
swim next to the shark
and gets i think a lot of the resources
that in most these companies they have
massive open source
initiatives and they're all mit licensed
and you have a great opportunity to take
advantage of a lot of that stuff
i mean that's a big reason why i feel so
confident in our decisions that we've
made for our tech stack is
you know we have github on our side we
have shopify we have
a number of other organizations out
there that are running at a scale
that i'd love to get to one day at
collide but i
certainly know it's going to be a while
before we get there but i know that when
we get there
they've been able to stay they've been
able to generate the tools necessary to
run
their preferred framework and language
at the scale that they need and we're
already experiencing
a wealth of resources and able to i
think solve problems more efficiently
like a great example of this is github
released a multi-database add-on to the
you know the version of rails that came
out i think last year where essentially
they have now moved on to sharding their
database because they need to at this
point like they're starting to get
tables that have you know hundreds of
millions of rows in them and now they
really need to start thinking about
sharding
or they need to start thinking about
read replication and those are
challenging issues to solve
and you need to be able to solve them in
a way that you know is going to scale up
you know 10x to where you are today and
you know
these are now making their way into the
framework and they're just options that
you can set and you just have the
benefit
of all that experience there's i think a
type of engineer that's out there that
really looks forward to solving those
problems more manually
but i think if you're doing the right
thing for your business you're trying to
set yourself up so that
the things that you're really applying
your computer science knowledge towards
are the really the unique problems that
your organization differentiates itself
in its ability to solve
like i think githubs would be you know
what are the ways that they can
translate get features into
great project management and source code
management
features and opportunities and i think
for collide like we should be focusing
on
you know how we can take endpoint
telemetry and really elevate and make it
easy to understand by security teams
we shouldn't really be focusing on how
we're going to really
you know combine you know fragments from
elastic with data from postgres and how
that all kind of plays together like
that's interesting work but it's not
necessarily work that we should have to
do
if we can avoid it yeah that makes sense
though you actually bring up an
interesting point and
we've kind of hopped around the tob
index quite a bit actually i think i'm
referring to the stack overflow release
which we'll put this in the show notes
i'll
post both the tob index and the stack
overflow developer survey
to list the most popular languages but
we've kind of hopped around a bit i
think
javascript was the first and then ruby's
actually sixth on the list but i'm going
to tie it back
to java here because one actually last
thing i'd like to ask about ruby
is choosing these sub languages so you
might choose ruby on rails but there's
actually a lot of different variants of
ruby so i think the original ruby is
written in c but there's also j ruby
which was written you know ruby's
written on top of the jvm
which would then relate back to java and
i guess scala as well too
so how do you think about choosing that
specifics of the tech stack
you know when do you find benefit from
choosing jruby versus ruby
yeah i think you bring up a really good
point and i think this applies
specifically to java
and jruby as well is when at first at
collide we weren't using heroku we were
using kubernetes
and we were you know creating docker
containers deploying things out to
kubernetes
and the first thing that we ran into was
there's just a lot of
friction between the sre team and the
team that was building
the product because the sizes of these
containers became astronomical like ruby
just is not
it's a compiled language you have a lot
of bundled in dependencies
and the container size can just get out
of control
and j ruby and just java in general when
you have these jar files
they're even bigger and suddenly you now
have
an arbitrary infrastructure choice
really now applying pressure on the
foundational choices that you're making
to build your product
and i think that that's backwards and
you really need to
ensure that if jruby you really want
like some of the performance
characteristics
of java obviously startup performance
isn't great but once you're actually
you know running a warmed up java
application you're going to see a lot
more
performance and ability to use
parallelization like you have access to
things that just aren't available to you
in the mri version like the reference
implementation of ruby that's the most
popular
but what i find so interesting about
this is that github actually started on
j ruby they were a huge j ruby shop
until about 2009 2010 and i think that
the
maturity of jruby they started to see i
think
they were just unable to overcome i
think a lot of the language bugs and
i think some of the performance
characteristics of things that just
weren't thought through
for jruby at that scale and they
actually had to
revert back to mri ruby and then you
know start solving the performance
challenges
directly by investing in that and i'll
have to do a little bit more research to
understand the specifics as to why
but i think that the advice here is that
you shouldn't let
the infrastructure dependencies dictate
i think the underlying languages that
are going to be the core parts of the
application
and that was an example where we were
shying away
inadvertently from ruby jruby the jvm in
general because we were worried about
how big these containers were going to
be in terms of how we had to deploy them
out there
and that was the wrong thing but i think
if you want some of the performance
characteristics
of java you want the parallelization and
you don't want the gill or
you know the global interpreter lock
jruby is a fine choice but
you're going to find a lot of
incompatibilities there and you're often
going to be solving a lot of bugs where
you're not on the well-trodden path
anymore you know just reaching for any
arbitrary gem isn't necessarily going to
be
the thing that wins and i think it's
useful to look at the
folks out there and look at the
decisions that they made and say okay
maybe we want to stay away from this
because
they know something that i don't counter
example though is twitter
where if you believe them and the the
hard time that they had around ruby and
rails
you know growing into that you know you
saw the fail whale all the time early
2009-2010
that would indicate that ruby was a
terrible choice and that it just doesn't
scale
uh luckily we have some good examples
now to prove that isn't true but
i think that was a big wake-up call to
folks who were looking to invest early
on in their product
and they were really worried about oh if
i'm successful i'm not going to be able
to get there
the last thing i'll cover just in
relation to this topic is
the ability to scale down i think a lot
of people worry about scaling up
and they're going to miss their shot
their opportunity to to be viral or to
you know
i think grow and like this will be a
huge limiter to their business
but oftentimes your idea your product is
going to do adequately
or below expectations and so how can you
actually scale down
the product in terms of how many people
are needed to run it and engineer it
so they can actually lower the cost of
goods sold and your cash burn in general
to actually retool the product find
different things to work on so that it's
actually successful in the market
and i think that's something that
engineer teams should really think about
if this isn't successful
are we setting ourselves for this is our
only shot or are we in a position where
we can scale this down and run at a slow
burn
with just a skeleton staff and if the
answer is no
then you better be sure that you're
right i mean you're really reducing the
amount of
chances that you have to make a
successful business that makes sense and
i know you focus pretty heavily on web
but
as it stands i thought the other two big
languages i would cover
in sort of this top five index include
java
and the net framework which i'll include
really is mostly c sharp but
i guess it includes f sharp and sort of
the whole asp.net
ecosystem so the fact is that still a
lot of people
are writing java in c sharp so when are
the good use cases for those because we
can't avoid
that they are very popular languages but
maybe they're not specifically suited
for web or you know they might be suited
for web because there are plenty of
frameworks for both of them asp.net
spring
hibernate grails so you know we can't
ignore that so
what's your take on the jvm the.net
frameworks
so i think that stack overflow is a
great example
of a product that has proven that you
can build
highly scalable successful web
application
in the net stack and the creators of
stack overflow
blogged a lot about this because i think
there's a
bias in maybe my age group and a little
bit younger than me
around picking i think more corporate
technologies but
if you pick these corporate technologies
i think that you have
number one is like microsoft is
incredible at documentation
you know every facet of that language
has been documented
ad nauseam and you just have that wealth
of information available to you and it's
tied in
so well with visual studio and vs code
is a great example of them really
extending a lot of their ability to
build ides
competently to other language
communities so
i'm really bullish on on microsoft's
ability to build i think a compelling
developer experience there and there's
companies out there today that have
proven
you can absolutely build a scalable web
application
in those languages i think where i don't
want to reach for those languages
and this is relevant to us at collide is
we also have an endpoint agent that we
run on your device and that's
primarily written in a combination of c
c plus plus and objective c
and windows is still very much
mired in like we hear our apis they're
all accessible in c
or c plus and yes we have like bridges
to be able to call the stuff
using.net but ultimately if you really
want the real deal
you really need to start you need to
just call this in the c function or
something like that
and i think if you're really trying to
build something where you're getting
telemetry about a device or you want to
really interact
with a native system api those are still
the languages that i would choose over
something more abstract
python is another example of of where
you might want to reach instead of
writing objective c there's like
pi objective c where if you were more
familiar with python you could kind of
wrap
a lot of the stuff in there what i
really like about go
is uh seago where you can just sort of
in comments write various c functions
and then call them with go i think
that's awesome
it's a great way to kind of mix that and
we have a little bit of go in
our endpoint agent as well and it's
great when i can just
write some objective c or c plus and and
then be able to then call
that directly in a go function is really
neat and i think that
you can start applying a lot of these
different languages and experiences
together and
a lot of languages really allow you to
tap into the
knowledge that you've invested before
and i think if you're doing anything
with native operating system apis is you
want to reach for those native languages
instead of going through
now you mentioned python as well too and
we can't ignore that one because that's
another big
one in the top three is it simple to say
that
python is a great choice for web as well
as sort of the data science ai because i
also find that python is very similar to
ruby in terms of how it's laid out it's
a scripting language
is very similar is do you have any
criteria in evaluating between python
and ruby and the similar that you could
evaluate between jvm and
net well i think you nailed it right
data sciences and artificial
intelligence
there has been no credible
efforts made on the ruby side or i think
like an equivalently
friendly language that compete with
tensorflow and the various other apis
that are available on python like
python is the obvious choice and i think
that the breadth of skill and
availability of great data science
people that are
familiar with that language they've been
taught it in
university i think python is a great
choice for that
if you're looking for those types of
skill sets i think you have a long road
ahead of you if you wanted to really do
some incredible stuff in ruby with ai
like there's just
the libraries just aren't there i think
you're gonna be having to do a lot of
original research
it's unfortunate that ruby wasn't in a
position where they could really attract
that community right away
because i think it's the language itself
it's nothing about python or ruby in
particular make it
well-versed for that it's just the
people that were more academically
interested in these concepts
tended to focus on writing their their
software in python and then things
really spun up from there so i think if
you really want a monolithic stack
and you're doing something with ai then
you have to choose python
otherwise if you're doing something on
the ruby side you're going to have a
really hard time
integrating those technologies and then
you're going to start reaching for
microservices
and then you're going to have a lot of
complexity that gets baked into your web
application there
and i think that those are the main
criteria that i'm thinking about when
i'm choosing python over something like
ruby at least personally
yep so now wrapping this up here in
terms of all the different technologies
to choose
you did mention that there's a couple of
that are just canonical like for sql
pretty much postgres
is the big one i know mysql can be sort
of a competitor as well as sql server so
i think it probably just depends on
what your stack is if you're using.net
probably a lot easier to use sql server
than postgres
with mobile right it's either old school
it's java new school is kotlin whereas
for ios
old school is objective c and new school
is swift and again same thing with
devops it's like you could either sort
of build it yourself with aws or
kubernetes or docker and then
on the sort of more managed solutions
you've got something like heroku
the last one i want to cover though it's
just it's cannot escape
the fold of the top five is php
now my hunch is that with php it's
there's so much grasp on it because
facebook employs a lot of people and
wordpress employs a lot of people
so between facebook and wordpress you've
got a bunch of php variants
do you think that's it or and it's just
it's in the top
five because a lot of people employ php
developers
or is there still space for building a
new greenfield project
in a php framework like laravel or
symphony
i've been so impressed by the level
framework and the community around it
in fact as someone who has invested in
the majority of my time
in the rails ecosystem we're starting to
actually take some of the ideas from
laravel
and incorporate them into that framework
into the rails framework because
they're just so far ahead i think the
thing that lareville really gets right
is they've identified who their audience
is it's mostly
b2c and b2b sas people want to build sas
applications and they
have distilled down the modules which in
and they're
many of them are actually paid that's
their business model and it's like
here's
the best most canonical way to do off
and laravel here's how you're going to
store
you know objects in s3 like the things
that you're just going to need
regardless of what type of app you're
building like they're just
the table stakes sas capabilities that
you're going to need like everybody's
going to need to upload an avatar like
you're going to need to be able to put
images in a bucket somewhere like and
you're going to need to deal with
cropping them and resizing them and you
know things like that like
everybody has to do that at some point
it doesn't matter what your web app is
they've just figured that out and they
make php
look good like the syntax and the apis
they're using like they're still
somewhat limited i think by
obviously the language itself and even
the creator of php would be the first to
admit that
you know nothing about language design
when he was really creating it and a lot
of the things that you really need to
write
i think confident couldn't feature we
were introduced after php5 like classes
like there was just no concept of php
was not even a full object-oriented
programming language
until the late 2000s so it's crazy to
see how much
facebook has i think influenced the
legitimacy of php and then now i think
there's a lot of great frameworks
based on that new influx of legitimacy
and proof of scale
where i think it would be a fine choice
i think you're right though i think
the majority like i've read a stat i
think that's at 76
of server side like if you were able to
detect the server-side language or the
majority of
websites that are out there php would be
the one that would make them up 76
so and i think a lot of that has got to
be wordpress or
you know similar types of content
management systems that are out there
but i think that there is a strong
passion of
of laravel and other i think cake php
like
that's one that i remember back in the
old days i think that have been subsumed
by like the laravel community so
i would choose laravel if you're
building a web sas application
in php and i think you're going to have
a great time doing it and i think you're
going to find really passionate people
to work for you and i think it'll be
performing enough and facebook has
proven that well jason this has been a
great conversation talking about these
greenfield projects today and i really
appreciate you going through all these
different tech stacks with me
so i want to close out with a kind of
rapid fire set of questions here
i'm just going to ask you just personal
recommendation
nothing else just i'm going to ask you
about a series of different kinds of
apps that you would build
and just kind of get your rapid fire
what language stack would you use for
them
ready okay all right web app for me ruby
on rails
back end and then i think front end i
really like the hot wire
library like actually putting html over
the wire to build the front end very
similar to phoenix live view
so ruby on rails obvious choice for me
there what about a sas product
it may not necessarily be it could be
on-prem installed doesn't necessarily
have to be
web driven like a standard web app yeah
i think that you're gonna have a hard
time building a sas product that doesn't
have some kind of web component to it
but i think they're out there i think
direct to app store there's good
examples of that so i think if you can
carve off your audience to just if you
can start with just apple
if that's where your audience is and you
don't need android right out of the gate
go with swift
swift ui and then you know something
like firebase or something for
you know actually persisting data okay
so i guess that probably answers my next
one which is mobile app
would be ios so you do swift yeah
definitely i think
if you asked me a year ago i'd say it's
important to learn objective c
still and you're going to need i think a
little bit more of ui kit
swift ui has come a long way wwdc is
right around the corner
i think it's good for you i think you
can just learn swift and swift ui now
and you're going to be in good shape to
build anything that you want
within reason desktop app desktop app so
i'm a mac user primarily
i'm going to want to reach for me
personally swift
swift ui again and i think there's a lot
of
great technologies that are coming out
that'll allow you to maybe re-leverage
that code and potentially use it in
other
like ipad os and ios itself when it
comes to
windows and linux i'm not the super
expert there and so
in my opinion if you need to have like a
multi-platform story
that's when you want to reach for
something like electron and i wouldn't
feel ashamed of that vs code is coded in
electron it's an incredible product that
works relatively well
and when you have text when you're
building a text editor
web browsers are great at text that's
what they're designed to do don't feel
shame in using electron if you're
building like an ide
you want to cross-platform it's a great
choice fintech focus
okay fintech i think you're going to
want to look at the comments in the
space and
i think a lot of them have a lot of
tech debt to work with i think you're
going to see a lot of python and fintech
in terms of like the newer languages
there i don't think you're going to see
a lot of ruby but
i don't know if you would consider yeah
i don't know not authoritative enough i
think to give a good recommendation
there
apis are really important i would really
think about choosing a language that's
going to allow you to build
a lot of microservices
microservices-based apis that are going
to be useful in the context of a greater
organization
for me personally that means reaching
for things like golang things that
i can just kind of get a nice
performance well-typed api out the door
yeah i've heard python also the same
reason for ai focus is because of its
integer and floating point precision
that's a big reason why it's so
successful
in the data science community is because
all the sort of linear algebra you have
to use
for the like scikit-learn is because of
the precision that's so high
in python with uh 32 and 64-bit integers
and that's a great point so i'm assuming
that for ai you would also choose python
absolutely yeah that's a no-brainer what
about blockchain
blockchain i think coinbase has proven
it out i'm a big fan
of ruby for blockchain obviously i'm not
an expert on blockchain in general but i
think that
you have a little bit more latitude
there in terms of building something
obviously
if we're talking about actually mining
things out of a blockchain
then we're talking about like very low
level gpu level stuff then so that's
going to be more c
c plus plus or you know you might
actually want to
understand like the actual micro code
that's actually used to build these gpus
but now we're getting in the weeds
con 42 is a new series of must-watch
tech conferences
it's online and free to attend with
hybrid events coming next year
com 42 conferences cover topics like
cloud sre
chaos engineering machine learning and
quantum computing as well as programming
languages including python golang
rust and javascript register for free at
conf42.com
sc radio that's conf
number four number two dot com slash
se radio see you there for the ultimate
answers
[Music]
all right very last question what other
framework would you consider for any
other application that we haven't
covered
any other framework you know i'm just
going to put a shout out there like i'm
really impressed with the erlang slash
elixir community otp in general
i think that they've gotten that mixture
right of
giving you enough productivity to build
a kind of a bunch of back-end services
that
kind of participate and work with a
really great front-end web application
which you can build in a framework
called phoenix
they have i think a really good non
javascript heavy
front-end story with like phoenix live
view and i know that
you know i think erlang and elixir are
well suited towards
a number of different products not
necessarily just a web app
discord i think is a great example of a
of an organization that
really is betting big on that community
and they're doing a great job
perfect well this was great i'm glad i
get all your feedback on this
jason thank you again so much for
talking with us today about
choosing tech stacks for your next
greenfield project
thanks hopefully i was helpful everybody
out there listening trying to make some
good decisions remember optimize for
your team first
and then for the problem at hand great
thank you so much
thanks for listening to sc radio an
educational program brought to you by
ieee software magazine
for more about the podcast including
other episodes visit our website at
se radio.net to provide feedback you can
comment on each episode on the website
or reach us on linkedin
facebook twitter or through our slack
channel at scradio.slack.com
you can also email us at team
sc-radio.net
this and all other episodes of sc radio
is licensed under creative commons
license 2.5
thanks for listening